/*
 * Dan Carpenter and Tim Saxe, 7/10/2015
 * Question lists for the NYS IQ Challenge
 */

var questions;
var hardQuestions;

function SetUpQuestions() {
    questions = [
		{ "question": "How much energy can you save using Compact fluorescent bulbs (CFLs) instead of incandescent bulbs?", "answer": "75%", "other1": "10%", "other2": "15%", "other3": "50%", "correct": "", "used": "", "category": "elec", "explanation": "Using energy efficient CFLs can save you 75% over incandescent bulbs and also help control your lighting costs and save money on your electricity bills." },
		{ "question": "Which of the following is most energy-efficient?", "answer": "LED bulb", "other1": "Incandescent bulb", "other2": "Compact Fluorescent bulb", "other3": "All are equally efficient", "correct": "", "used": "", "category": "elec", "explanation": "Both LEDs and CFLs are more efficient than incandescent bulbs, but LEDs use the least amount of energy and last longer." },
		{ "question": "LEDs are energy efficient light bulbs.  What does LED stand for?", "answer": "Light Emitting Diode", "other1": "Like Energy Dividers", "other2": "Low Energy Demand", "other3": "None are correct", "correct": "", "used": "", "category": "elec", "explanation": "LED bulbs are made with Light Emitting Diodes and use significantly less energy while lasting up to 25 times longer than incandescent bulbs." },
		{ "question": "Electricity is measured in:", "answer": "Kilowatt hours", "other1": "Kilowatt days", "other2": "Megawatt seconds", "other3": "Therm hours", "correct": "", "used": "", "category": "elec", "explanation": "A measure of electricity defined 1 kilowatt (1,000 watts) of power expended for 1 hour. The kilowatt-hour is used as a billing unit for energy delivered to consumers by electric utilities." },
		{ "question": "What does kWh stand for?", "answer": "Kilowatt hours", "other1": "Keep Watts Home", "other2": "Keeps Well Heated", "other3": "None are correct", "correct": "", "used": "", "category": "elec", "explanation": "A measure of electricity defined as energy measured as 1 kilowatt (1,000 watts) of power expended for 1 hour." },
		{ "question": "If the power goes out in your home, what is the first thing you should do?", "answer": "Check neighbors or streetlights to see if they have power", "other1": "Clean out the refrigerator", "other2": "Flush the toilet", "other3": "Leave a light on for when the power returns", "correct": "", "used": "", "category": "elec", "explanation": "If they have power, you may have simply blown a fuse or tripped a circuit breaker in your home. If that is not the cause, call your utility to report the outage." },
		{ "question": "When a power outage occurs in your neighborhood, what does the utility company restore first?", "answer": "Transmission lines and power stations", "other1": "The elderly", "other2": "Hospitals and nursing homes", "other3": "Animal shelters and zoos", "correct": "", "used": "", "category": "elec", "explanation": "Making repairs to the power lines and transmission equipment is first priority of the utility. These repairs must be made before other services can be restored." },
		{ "question": "Refrigerators run 24/7.  How can you save money on refrigerators?", "answer": "Choose energy efficient models", "other1": "Buy food that does not need to be kept cold", "other2": "Turn them off at night", "other3": "Store food outdoors", "correct": "", "used": "", "category": "elec", "explanation": "You should choose energy efficient models to save money." },
		{ "question": "The US Dept. of Energy sponsors a program that rates appliances based on efficiency.  What is the program?", "answer": "Energy Star", "other1": "Power Star", "other2": "Energy Saver", "other3": "Star Saver", "correct": "", "used": "", "category": "elec", "explanation": "ENERGY STAR is a U.S. Environmental Protection Agency voluntary program that helps businesses and individuals save money and protect our climate through superior energy efficiency." },
		{ "question": "During the summer, what is the best way to conserve energy while staying cool?", "answer": "Use a ceiling fan", "other1": "Stand in front of an open refrigerator", "other2": "Move to Alaska", "other3": "Set the air conditioner to the coldest setting", "correct": "", "used": "", "category": "elec", "explanation": "Fans use 80% less energy than air conditioners and often can provide the same level of comfort." },
		{ "question": "Over time, what costs more, a $10 compact fluorescent light bulb or a $1 incandescent light bulb?", "answer": "Incandescent light bulb", "other1": "Compact fluorescent light bulb", "other2": "It depends on the appliance", "other3": "Both cost the same", "correct": "", "used": "", "category": "elec", "explanation": "Incandescent bulbs costs more because CFLs use less energy and last 10 times longer." },
		{ "question": "What can help make your freezer run more efficiently?", "answer": "Fill empty spaces with large bags of ice", "other1": "Only freeze vegetables", "other2": "Place on coldest setting", "other3": "None are correct", "correct": "", "used": "", "category": "elec", "explanation": "Efficiency of a freezer is increased by keeping it full but be sure not to block the circulating fan." },
		{ "question": "An Energy Service Company must provide its residential customers with an:", "answer": "ESCO Consumer Bill of Rights", "other1": "ESCO Constitution", "other2": "ESCO Notice of Service", "other3": "None are correct", "correct": "", "used": "", "category": "energy", "explanation": "ESCOs can be large corporations or small businesses, which compete to sell you electricity. Your utility delivers your energy, but you can choose to purchase energy from your utility or an ESCO." },
		{ "question": "HEAP is a program that helps New Yorkers pay for utility service.  What does the acronym HEAP stand for?", "answer": "Home Energy Assistance Program", "other1": "Home Economics And Protection program", "other2": "Home Environmental Aid Program", "other3": "Home Efficiency Appliance Program ", "correct": "", "used": "", "category": "energy", "explanation": "HEAP is a federally funded program which assists low income New Yorkers with the cost of heating their homes." },
		{ "question": "An ESCO offers electricity and/or natural gas supply to customers in NYS.  What does the acronym ESCO stand for?", "answer": "Energy Service Company", "other1": "Efficiency Standard Co-op", "other2": "Environmental Supply Corporation", "other3": "Equal Service for Communities", "correct": "", "used": "", "category": "energy", "explanation": "ESCOs can be large corporations or small businesses, which compete to sell you electricity. Your utility delivers your energy, but you can choose to purchase energy from your utility or an ESCO." },
		{ "question": "Natural gas is transported mainly by:", "answer": "Pipelines", "other1": "Cars", "other2": "Trains", "other3": "Planes", "correct": "", "used": "", "category": "gas", "explanation": "The natural gas transportation system consists of a complex network of pipelines, designed to move gas from its origin to areas of high natural gas demand." },
		{ "question": "What country is the leading producer in natural gas?", "answer": "United States", "other1": "Canada", "other2": "China", "other3": "Russia", "correct": "", "used": "", "category": "gas", "explanation": "The United States is the top producer of natural gas.  Russia, Canada and China are among the top ten producers." },
		{ "question": "What utility service does the NYS Public Service Commission regulate?", "answer": "All are correct", "other1": "Gas", "other2": "Electric", "other3": "Water", "correct": "", "used": "", "category": "misc", "explanation": "The Public Service Commission regulates electric, gas, steam, telecommunications, water utilities, and cable industry of New York state." },
		{ "question": "Which system uses the most energy in the average home?", "answer": "Heating and cooling rooms", "other1": "Lighting", "other2": "Refrigeration", "other3": "Water heating", "correct": "", "used": "", "category": "misc", "explanation": "Heating and cooling make up about 42% of household energy use, water heating is about 14%, refrigeration about 8%, lights about 8%, and all other appliances combined make up about 28%." },
		{ "question": "What does the PSC stand for in NYSPSC?", "answer": "Public Service Commission", "other1": "Periodic Sample Count", "other2": "Primary Supply Center", "other3": "Program Support Center", "correct": "", "used": "", "category": "misc", "explanation": "The Public Service Commission regulates electric, gas, steam, telecommunications, water utilities, and cable industry of New York state." },
		{ "question": "Solar, geothermal, biomass, and wind are all forms of what type of energy?", "answer": "Renewable", "other1": "Kinetic", "other2": "Fusion", "other3": "Aerobic", "correct": "", "used": "", "category": "misc", "explanation": "Renewable energy is generally defined as energy that comes from resources that are not significantly depleted by their use, such as sunlight, wind, rain, tides, waves and geothermal heat." },
		{ "question": "HEFPA is a law to protect utility consumers.  What does HEFPA stand for?", "answer": "Home Energy Fair Practices Act", "other1": "High Energy Free Power Act", "other2": "Home Electricity and Farmers Power Authority", "other3": "Harmless and Emission-Free Pollution Absorption", "correct": "", "used": "", "category": "misc", "explanation": "HEFPA stands for the Home Energy Fair Practices Act." },
		{ "question": "What supplies are recommended during a power outage?", "answer": "All are correct", "other1": "Battery-powered radio", "other2": "Flashlight", "other3": "Water", "correct": "", "used": "", "category": "misc", "explanation": "Prepare for an outage by having supplies on hand like water, non-perishable food and medicines, flashlights and a telephone that does not require electricity." },
		{ "question": "What number should you call to have buried utility lines located before digging for construction?", "answer": "811", "other1": "1-800-WatchIt", "other2": "1-888-Digging", "other3": "None are correct", "correct": "", "used": "", "category": "misc", "explanation": "Contractors, property owners, etc. planning excavation should dial 811 to contact Dig Safely NY, a call center that works with utilities to help prevent damages to underground facilities." },
		{ "question": "The Office of the PSC of Telecommunications oversees what type of companies?", "answer": "Telecommunications and cable ", "other1": "Waste management and insurance ", "other2": "Water and sewer ", "other3": "None are correct", "correct": "", "used": "", "category": "tele", "explanation": "The Office of Telecommunications is responsible for overseeing the performance of the telecommunication and cable television companies under Commission jurisdiction." },
		{ "question": "Telephone service can be provided by which of the following?", "answer": "All are correct", "other1": "Broadband", "other2": "Landline", "other3": "Wireless/mobile", "correct": "", "used": "", "category": "tele", "explanation": "There are four basic types of telephone service: wireless, cable TV-based, Internet-based and traditional wireline service.  Availability of services may vary so consumers should contact carriers directly for coverage information." },
		{ "question": "Who do you call to apply for Lifeline Discounted Telephone Service?", "answer": "Your phone service provider", "other1": "The Office of Attorney General", "other2": "The Department of Public Service  (DPS)", "other3": "The Federal Communication Commission  (FCC)", "correct": "", "used": "", "category": "tele", "explanation": "Lifeline is offered by many telephone providers, including some wireless and cable companies, to help income-eligible consumers save money on their phone bills." },
		{ "question": "Participation in which of these assistance programs can qualify a person for Lifeline Discount Telephone Service?", "answer": "All are correct", "other1": "Supplementary Security Income  (SSI)", "other2": "Medicaid", "other3": "Free Lunch Program", "correct": "", "used": "", "category": "tele", "explanation": "In New York, a person may qualify for Lifeline telephone discounts if they are income eligible or participate in qualifying assistance program." },
		{ "question": "The lowest level of television cable service is called", "answer": "Basic cable", "other1": "Ordinary cable", "other2": "Premium cable", "other3": "Satellite service", "correct": "", "used": "", "category": "tele", "explanation": "Basic cable includes local broadcast television stations and any public, educational, or government access channels required by the system's franchise agreement." },
		{ "question": "Every cable television company must notify subscribers in writing about:", "answer": "All are correct", "other1": "Billing procedures", "other2": "Credit for outages", "other3": "Payment requirements", "correct": "", "used": "", "category": "tele", "explanation": "This notice must be provided annually to new subscribers, at the time of installation, and to all subscribers when there is a change in the company's billing or payment practices." },
		{ "question": "If your faucet leaks 1 drip per second, how many gallons will that add up to in a day?", "answer": "5 gallons", "other1": "100 gallons", "other2": "15 gallons", "other3": "250 gallons", "correct": "", "used": "", "category": "water", "explanation": "It takes about 15,140 drips to equal a gallon, therefore a drip per second would equal approximately 5.7 gallons in a day.  To conserve water, check all your taps, pipes and plumbing fixtures for leaks and drips." },
		{ "question": "What is an effective way to save money on your water bills?", "answer": "All are correct", "other1": "Take shorter showers", "other2": "Fix leaky faucets", "other3": "Install low-flow shower heads", "correct": "", "used": "", "category": "water", "explanation": "You can lower your water costs by using less water and taking steps to repair water-wasting leaks." },
		{ "question": "What is an energy efficient temperature for your water heater?", "answer": "120 degrees", "other1": "175 degrees", "other2": "180 degrees", "other3": "212 degrees", "correct": "", "used": "", "category": "water", "explanation": "Water heating is the second largest energy expense in your home. To save energy, set your water heater no higher than 120 degrees F or about midway between the low and medium settings." },
		{ "question": "What label rating should be used when purchasing dishwashers that will save you money on your water bill?", "answer": "Energy Star", "other1": "4 Star", "other2": "Star Rewards", "other3": "Star Wars", "correct": "", "used": "", "category": "water", "explanation": "ENERGY STAR certified dishwashers use advanced technology to get your dishes clean while using less water and energy." },
		{ "question": "Which of these items/activities wastes the MOST water per day in the average home? ", "answer": "A leaky toilet", "other1": "Running the tap while washing dishes.", "other2": "Brushing your teeth with the water running.", "other3": "Old waterheaters.", "correct": "", "used": "", "category": "water", "explanation": "A leaky toilet can waste about 200 gallons of water every day." },
		{ "question": "Which of these activities will save money on water heating bills? ", "answer": "Buying a more efficient water heater", "other1": "All are correct", "other2": "Using a garbage disposal", "other3": "Taking long showers", "correct": "", "used": "", "category": "water", "explanation": "Buying a more efficient water heater will save you money on water heating bills." },
		{ "question": "Which appliance uses the most energy?", "answer": "Hot water heater", "other1": "Hair dryer", "other2": "Television", "other3": "Clothes dryer", "correct": "", "used": "", "category": "water", "explanation": "Water heaters account for nearly 17 percent of a home's energy use, consuming more energy than all other household appliances combined. " }
    ]

    hardQuestions = [
		{ "question": "How much of the Earth's water is available for everyday use?", "answer": "Less than 1%", "other1": "More than 50%", "other2": "28%", "other3": "12%", "correct": "", "used": "", "category": "water", "explanation": "Although 75% of the surface of the earth is covered by water, less than 1% is available for people to use. The rest is salt water, frozen in polar ice caps and glaciers, or locked in inaccessible locations underground." },
		{ "question": "How much water is saved per flush with a high-efficiency toilet?", "answer": "Between 2 and 6 gallons", "other1": "Less than 1 gallon", "other2": "Too little to measure", "other3": "More than 6 gallons", "correct": "", "used": "", "category": "water", "explanation": "Toilets made before 1992 use between 3.5 to 7 gallons per flush. New high-efficiency models use less than 1.3 gallons per flush-up to 80 percent less water." },
		{ "question": "What is the average amount of energy that can be saved by turning the thermostat down 10 degrees at night?", "answer": "10%", "other1": "0%", "other2": "25%", "other3": "52%", "correct": "", "used": "", "category": "elec", "explanation": "Over an eight hour period about 1% is saved for each degree the temperature is lowered." },
		{ "question": "What percentage of power consumed by incandescent bulbs gets wasted in the form of heat?", "answer": "85%", "other1": "20%", "other2": "50%", "other3": "65%", "correct": "", "used": "", "category": "elec", "explanation": "Incandescent lightbulbs heat a wire filament until it glows.  Only a small portion of the energy is converted to light and the rest is lost as heat." },
		{ "question": "One way gas usage is measured by:", "answer": "Therms", "other1": "Kilowatt hours", "other2": "Gallons", "other3": "Flow rate", "correct": "", "used": "", "category": "gas", "explanation": "Natural Gas is usually measured by volume and is stated in cubic feet.  A \"therm\" is used to denote 100 cubic feet." },
		{ "question": "Natural gas volume is measured by cubic feet.  What is heat content measured in?", "answer": "British Thermal Units (BTU)", "other1": "Revolving Battery Igniters (RBI)", "other2": "Terajoules", "other3": "Australian Temperature Ratings (ATR)", "correct": "", "used": "", "category": "gas", "explanation": " British Thermal Units (BTU) measure heat content. " },
		{ "question": "How many Lifeline discounts can a qualifying household have?", "answer": "1", "other1": "10", "other2": "2", "other3": "5", "correct": "", "used": "", "category": "tele", "explanation": " Only one Lifeline discount is allowed per household, consisting of either wireline or wireless service." },
		{ "question": "Having your telephone service switched to another provider without your permission is known as:", "answer": "Slamming", "other1": "Phishing", "other2": "Switching", "other3": "Cramming", "correct": "", "used": "", "category": "tele", "explanation": "Slamming is the switching of your local, regional or long-distance service from one company to another without your permission." },
		{ "question": "Who is the current Chair of the NYS Public Service Commission?", "answer": "Audrey Zibelman", "other1": "Andrew Cuomo", "other2": "Bill DeBlasio", "other3": "Thomas DiNapoli", "correct": "", "used": "", "category": "water", "explanation": "The current chair of the NYS Public Service Commission is Audrey Zibelman." },
		{ "question": "How many Commissioners make up the PSC?", "answer": "5", "other1": "4", "other2": "6", "other3": "7", "correct": "", "used": "", "category": "elec", "explanation": "There are five Commissioners that make up the Public Service Commission." }
    ]
}

